Guide to the Jonathan E. Cox Papers, 1885-1938 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Jonathan E. Cox papers 1885-1938 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Cox, Jonathan Elwood, 1856-1932.
30 Linear Feet Approximately 46,057 Items
Banker and manufacturer of High Point, N.C. May have been a Quaker.
The Jonathan E. Cox Papers chiefly consist of the business records of a banker and manufacturer from High Point, North Carolina. Records date from 1885-1938 and include many boxes of business and personal correspondence, chiefly letters to Cox; and a series of manuscript volumes, including journals, daybooks, order books, trial balance books, ledgers, profit-and-loss accounts, bill books, inventory records, rent book, check stubs, mill contracts, a letter book, and an account book of Joseph D. Cox. There are few personal items, but there is some biographical information on Cox's daughter, Clara I. Cox, a Quaker also living in High Point, who was active in civic and humanitarian affairs in that city.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jonathan E. Cox Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1956.
Collection Overview
The Jonathan E. Cox Papers chiefly consist of the business records of a banker and manufacturer from High Point, North Carolina. Records date from 1885-1938 and include many boxes of business and personal correspondence, chiefly to Cox from suppliers, builders, creditors, and manufacturers; and a series of manuscript volumes, including journals, daybooks, order books, trial balance books, ledgers, profit-and-loss accounts, bill books, inventory records, rent book, check stubs, mill contracts, a letter book, and an account book of Joseph D. Cox. Business topics in the manuscripts and correspondence include banks and banking, insurance, textile industry, lumber trade, shipping, and the mercantile business. There are few personal items, but there is some biographical information on Cox's daughter, Clara I. Cox, a Quaker also living in High Point, who was active in civic and humanitarian affairs in that city. There is significant political correspondence, chiefly for 1908, when Cox was an unsuccessful candidate on the Republican ticket for governor of North Carolina. Among other subjects represented are universities and colleges (Guilford and Peabody, later part of Vanderbilt University), North Carolina roads, and American participation in World War I. Records are arranged in chronological order with the exception of the last three boxes, which contain the earliest material. Manuscript volumes are housed separately.
Related Material
North Carolina ledger, 1894-1898. Ledger of an unidentified merchant probably located in High Point, N.C. Transactions in the volume primarily show the sale of food, although there is occasional mention of clothing and household items. Contains account for Jonathan E. Cox.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Banks and banking -- North Carolina
Cox, Clara I.
Cox, Joe (Joseph D.)
Cox, Jonathan Elwood, 1856-1932
George Peabody College for Teachers
Governors -- North Carolina
Guilford College
Industries -- North Carolina
Insurance companies -- North Carolina
Lumber trade -- North Carolina
North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
Republican Party (N.C.)
Roads -- North Carolina
Textile industry -- North Carolina
Universities and colleges -- Southern States
Vanderbilt University. George Peabody College for Teachers -- History
World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, American
Contents of Collection
- Business Papers Series, 1903-1921 and undated, (38 boxes)
  For the earliest business correpondence from 1898-1903, see boxes 40-42.
  - 1903 Feb.-Apr. (Box 1)
  - 1903 May-July (Box 2)
  - 1903 Aug.-Oct. (Box 3)
  - 1903 Nov.-Dec. and n.d. (Box 4)
  - 1904 Jan.-Mar. (Box 5)
  - 1904 Apr.-Dec. and n.d. (Box 6)
  - 1905-1906, Sept. (Box 7)
  - 1906 Oct.-1906 Dec. and n.d. (Box 8)
  - 1907 Jan.-1907 Mar. (Box 9)
  - 1907 Apr.-1907 July (Box 10)
  - 1907 Aug.-1907 Dec. and n.d. (Box 11)
  - 1908 Jan.-1908 Aug. (Box 12)
  - 1908 Jan.-1908 Dec. (Box 13)
  - 1909 Jan.-1909 June (Box 14)
  - 1909 July-1909 Dec. and n.d. (Box 15)
  - 1910 May-1910 Dec. (Box 16)
  - 1910 Jan.-1910 Apr. (Box 17)
  - 1911 (Box 18)
  - 1912 (Box 19)
  - 1913 Jan.-1913 July (Box 20)
  - 1913 Aug.-1913 Dec. (Box 21)
  - 1914 Jan.-1914 May (Box 22)
  - 1914 June-1914 Sept. (Box 23)
  - 1914 Oct.-1914 Dec. and n.d. (Box 24)
  - 1915 Jan.-1915 Apr. (Box 25)
  - 1915 May-1915 Sept. (Box 26)
  - 1915 Oct.-1915 Dec. and n.d. (Box 27)
  - 1916 Jan.-1916 June (Box 28)
  - 1916 July-1916 Dec. and n.d. (Box 29)
  - 1917 Jan.-1917 June (Box 30)
  - 1917 July-1917 Dec. and n.d. (Box 31)
  - 1918 Jan.-1918 May (Box 32)
  - 1918 June-1918 Dec. (Box 33)
  - 1919 (Box 34)
  - 1920 Jan.-1920 June (Box 35)
  - 1920 July-1920 Dec. and n.d. (Box 36)
  - 1921 Jan.-1921 June (Box 37)
  - 1921 July-1921 Dec. and undated (Box 38)
- Additional Printed Material Series, 1920-1924, (1 box)
  - Clippings and various printed material (Box 39)
- Original accession, 1898-1938, (3 boxes)
  Probably the first boxes acquired of this collection. Business correspondence and records, chiefly correspondence to J. Cox from suppliers, creditors, and insurance agencies pertaining to the lumber, textile, and shipping industry in North Carolina, to the establishment of a wagon wheel factory, and to various building projects. Box 40 also includes biographical information on Cox's daughter, Clara I. Cox, a Quaker of High Point, N.C. who was active in civic and humanitarian affaird in that city, and a photocopy of the residence of Jonathan Cox in High Point.
  - Business and personal papers, 1898-1938 (Box 40-42)
- Manuscript Volumes Series, 1885-1931, (57 volumes)
  Bound manuscript volumes belonging to the Cox manufacturing firm and to Jonathan Cox: daybooks, journals, ledgers, trial balance books, personal accounts, receipt books, inventories, and orders. See catalog record listings for individual volumes and their dates and locations.